# Christian Cabrera

Research Associate, Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge

103 Burkitt Walk, Cambridge
United Kingdom

⊠ chc79@cam.ac.uk

https://cabrerac.github.io/

I am a research associate in the ML@CL group at the Department of Computer Science and Technology of the University of Cambridge. I received a Ph.D. degree in Computer Science from Trinity College Dublin in 2020. My current research addresses the problems and challenges arising from deploying Artificial Intelligence systems in the real world. I am investigating the intersection between AI, systems, and software engineering to develop novel approaches for designing, building, monitoring, and adapting real-world AI-based systems. I am the author of more than 20 scientific papers published in top conferences and journals in the domains of Service-Oriented Computing, Pervasive Computing, and the Internet of Things.

# Education

June 2020

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland.

Dissertation: uDiscovery: An Urban-Centric Model for Service Discovery in Smart Cities.

Supervisor: Prof. Siobhán Clarke

Research focus on the IoT service discovery and composition problems in large, dynamic, and

distributed networks.

September 2014 M.Sc. in Systems and Computer Engineering, Los Andes University, Bogotá, Colombia.

Master's Dissertation: MOWL: A Domain Specific Language for Handling Modular Ontologies.

Research focus on knowledge management to integrate multiple knowledge models.

GPA: 4.37/5.0

September 2011 B.Sc. in Systems Engineering, Universidad de Nariño, Pasto, Colombia.

GPA: 4.06/5.0

## Experience

March 2021 Current **Research Associate**, Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge, United Kingdom.

Current research on the problem of deploying Al-based systems in the real world as part of the AutoAl project. Particularly, I am exploring and developing the *Data-Oriented Architectures* concept to enable the design and monitoring of Al-based systems The ultimate goal of this research is to ensure Al-based systems perform robustly, safely, and accurately in their deployed environment.

October 2021 Current **Teaching Assistant**, Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge, United Kingdom.

Advanced Data Science, Bachelors course: Designing the course material around the challenges data scientists face in reality. Supporting students' progress in laboratory sessions.

May 2019 February 2021

Research Assistant (May 2019 - Jun 2020) - Research Fellow (Jun 2020 - Feb 2021), School of Computer Science and Statistics, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland. Research on the provision of context-aware, pervasive and resilient applications in large and dynamic urban environments. Particularly, exploring the self-adaptive organisation of services information based on RL algorithms in smart cities, and the dynamic and proactive service placement problem at the edge based on meta-heuristic and prediction models.

**Teaching Assistant**, School of Computer Science and Statistics, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland.

March 2015 February 2021

Advanced Software Engineering, Master's course, What is the Internet doing to to me?, TCD elective course, Scalable Computing, Master's course, Systems Programming I, 2nd year Bachelors course, and Programming Project, 1st year Bachelors course.

August 2014 Software Project Lead, Conecta-TE, Los Andes University, Bogotá, Colombia.

December 2014 Work on analysis, design and development of software to support educational processes.

February 2012 Research Graduate Assistant, Systems Engineering Department, Los Andes University,

July 2014 Bogotá, Colombia.

Research on the semantic web, learning objects, and mobile learning.

Master's thesis. Design and implementation of a domain-specific language to handle modular ontologies.

February 2011 **Software Developer**, CJT&T Software Engineering, Pasto, Colombia.

December 2011 Work on analysis, design and development of software.

# Awards, and Scholarships

#### **Awards**

November 2018 Ph.D. Final Year Trinity Employability Award, in partnership with Intel. Dublin, Ireland.

November 2011 Best B.Sc. Research Final Project, Universidad de Narińo, Pasto, Colombia.

#### **Scholarships**

March 2015 Ph.D. research studentship in Dynamic Service Adaptation, Science Foundation Ireland, Dublin, Ireland.

# Supervision

#### **Undergrad Students**

June 2019 Elizabeth Rojas, Universidad de Nariño, Colombia.

December 2019 Thesis topic: Decision-making support tools for urban planners and authorities.

# Service to the Scientific Community

#### Roles in Academic Journals

Current **Reviewer for international peer-reviewed journals**, *IEEE Transactions on Services Computing (TSC)*, and *IEEE Internet of Things Journal*.

2022 **Co-organiser**, Challenges in Deploying and Monitoring Machine Learning Systems, NeurlPS Virtual Workshop.

2022 Co-organiser, NeurlPS at Cambridge Meetup, NeurlPS Satellite Event.

2022 **Co-organiser**, ATI AI Fellows day at Cambridge.

2020-2021 **PC Member**, International Joint Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multi-agent Systems (AAMAS).

#### **Publications**

## Peer-Reviewed Journals

- J5 Cabrera C., Svorobej S., Palade A., Kazmi A., Clarke S., MAACO: A Dynamic Service Placement Model for Smart Cities. *IEEE Transactions on Services Computing (TSC)*, IEEE, Early Access 2022.
- J4 Cabrera C., Clarke S., A self-adaptive service discovery model for smart cities. *IEEE Transactions on Services Computing (TSC)*, Vol. 15, No. 1, pp. 386-399, IEEE 2022.
- J3 Tabatabaee H., Rasool S., Kazmi A., Palade A., Cabrera C., White G., Clarke S., Dynamic Service Placement in Multi-access Edge Computing: a Systematic Literature Review. *IEEE Access*, Vol. 10, pp. 32639-32688, IEEE 2022.

- J2 Rojas E., Bastidas V., Cabrera C., Cities-Board: A Framework to Automate the Development of Smart Cities Dashboards. IEEE Internet of Things Journal, Vol. 7, pp. 10128-10136, IEEE 2020.
- J1 Palade A., **Cabrera C.**, Li F., White G., Razzaque MA., Clarke S., Middleware for internet of things: an evaluation in a small-scale IoT environment. *Journal of Reliable Intelligent Environments*, Vol. 4, pp. 3-23, SpringerLink 2018.

#### Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

- C16 Paleyes A., **Cabrera C.**, Lawrence N., An Empirical Evaluation of Flow Based Programming in the Machine Learning Deployment Context. *Proceedings of the 1st International Conference on AI Engineering: Software Engineering for AI*, 2022.
- C15 Paleyes A., **Cabrera C.**, Lawrence N., Towards Better Data Discovery and Collection with Flow-Based Programming. *Neurips Data-Centric AI Workshop (DCAI)*, 2021.
- C14 Cabrera C., Clarke S., A Reinforcement Learning-Based Service Model for the Internet of Things. International Conference on Service-Oriented Computing (ICSOC), pp. 790-799, SpringerLink 2021.
- C13 Palade A., Mukhopadhyay A., Kazmi A., **Cabrera C.**, Nomayo E., Iosifidis G., Ruffini M., Clarke S., A Swarm-based Approach for Function Placement in Federated Edges. *IEEE International Conference on Services Computing (SCC)*, IEEE 2020.
- C12 Cabrera C., Palade A., White G., Clarke S., An Urban-driven Service Request Management Model. *IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom)*, IEEE (2020).
- C11 Li F., Cabrera C., Clarke S., A WS-Agreement Based SLA Ontology for IoT Services. *International Conference on Internet of Things*, pp. 58-72, SpringerLink 2019.
- C10 White G., Palade A., Cabrera C., Clarke S., Autoencoders for QoS Prediction at the Edge. IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom), IEEE 2019.
- C9 Cabrera C., Palade A., White G., Clarke S., Services in IoT: A Service Planning Model based on Consumer Feedback. *International Conference on Service-Oriented Computing (ICSOC)*, pp. 304-313, SpringerLink 2018.
- C8 Palade A., **Cabrera C.**, White G., Clarke S., Stigmergic Service Composition and Adaptation in Mobile Environments. *International Conference on Service-Oriented Computing (ICSOC)*, pp. 618-633 SpringerLink 2018.
- C7 White G., **Cabrera C.**, Palade A., Clarke S., Augmented Reality in IoT. Workshop on Context-Aware and IoT Services (CloTS) in the International Conference on Service-Oriented Computing (ICSOC), pp. 149-160, SpringerLink 2018.
- Cabrera C., Palade A., White G., Clarke S., The Right Service at the Right Place: A Service Model for Smart Cities. IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (PerCom), IEEE 2018.
- C5 White G., Palade A., **Cabrera C.**, Clarke S., IoTPredict: Collaborative QoS Prediction in IoT. *IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (Per-Com)*, IEEE 2018.
- C4 White G., Palade A., Cabrera C., Clarke S., Quantitative Evaluation of QoS Prediction in IoT. 47th Annual IEEE/IFIP International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks Workshops (DSN-W 2017), IEEE 2017.
- C3 Cabrera C., Li F., Nallur V., Palade A., White G., Razzaque MA., Clarke S., Implementing heterogeneous, autonomous, and resilient services in IoT: an experience report. *IEEE 18th International Symposium on A World of Wireless, Mobile and Multimedia Networks (WoWMoM)*, IEEE 2017.

- C2 Palade A., **Cabrera C.**, White G., Razzaque MA., Clarke S., Middleware for Internet of Things: A quantitative evaluation in small scale. *IEEE 18th International Symposium on A World of Wireless, Mobile and Multimedia Networks (WoWMoM)*, IEEE 2017.
- C1 **Cabrera C.**, Palade A., Clarke S., An evaluation of service discovery protocols in the internet of things. *17th Proceedings of the Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC)*, pp. 469-476, ACM 2017.

# References

Current supervisor

**Prof. Neil Lawrence**, *DeepMind Professor of Machine Learning at University of Cambridge*, Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge, William Gates Building, 15 JJ Thomson Avenue, Cambridge.

Email: ndl21@cam.ac.uk

Current supervisor

**Dr. Carl Henrik Ek**, *Associate Professor at University of Cambridge*, Department of Computer Science and Technology, University of Cambridge, William Gates Building, 15 JJ Thomson Avenue, Cambridge.

Email: che29@cam.ac.uk

Ph.D. Thesis supervisor

**Prof. Siobhán Clarke**, *Professor at Trinity College Dublin*, School of Computer Science and Statistics, College Green, Dublin 2, Ireland.

Email: Siobhan.Clarke@scss.tcd.ie